A Finding Aid to the Valentine Gallery Records, circa 1890-1960, in the Archives of American Art aaa.valegall
Archives of American Art
Valentine Gallery records
circa 1890-circa 1960
aaa.valegall
Archives of American Art
1.8 Linear feet
The records of the New York City based Valentine Gallery measure 1.8 linear feet and date from circa 1890 to 1960. The bulk of the material documents the gallery's dealings with artists Louis Eilshemius, John Kane, Henri Matisse, and C.S. Price. Additionally, there is one scrapbook which contains printed materials regarding Valentine Gallery exhibitions from 1925-1936.
Valentine Gallery.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 2 series.
Series 1: Artists Files, circa 1890-1960 (Box 1, 3; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 2: Scrapbook, 1925-1936 (Box 2, 4; 0.5 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
The Valentine Gallery was founded by F. Valentine Dudensing in 1924 and operated in New York City until 1948. The gallery hosted many exhibitions of Modern European art and specialized in School of Paris paintings.
F. Valentine Dudensing was born in 1892 in New York City. His father, Richard Dudensing was a well known art publisher and gallerist who owned the engraving firm R. Dudensing and Son. Valentine served in World War I in the United States Aviation Corps and in 1918, married Hortense Garside. During a trip to Europe in the early 1920s, Dudensing became acquainted with the son of artist Henri Matisse, Pierre. Together, they conceived a gallery managed by Dudensing in New York while Matisse organized and curated art from Europe.
Dudensing opened his gallery in 1924 at 45 W.44th Street in New York City, the former location of his father's art publishing business. First known as Dudensing Gallery, the establishment was renamed F. Valentine Dudensing (1926) and finally changed to Valentine Gallery. The gallery was one of the first to bring Modern European works to New York City and hosted exhibitions of Giorgio de Chirico, Jean Lurçat, Henri Matisse, Pablo Picasso, and André Dunoyer de Segonzac. Additionally, Valentine Gallery represented American artists including Louis Eilshemius, John Kane, and C.S. Price. Pierre Matisse left the partnership with Valentine Dudensing to open his own gallery in 1931.
In 1948, Valentine Dudensing closed his gallery and moved to France with his wife. He died around 1967.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Valentine Gallery records were donated by gallery founder, Valentine Dudensing in 1958. Some materials regarding Louis Eilshemius were donated by Roy R. Neuberger in 1959. Neuberger received the Eilshemius material from Valentine Dudensing.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the New York City based Valentine Gallery measure 1.8 linear feet and date from circa 1890 to 1960. The bulk of the material documents the gallery's dealings with artists Louis Eilshemius, John Kane, Henri Matisse, and C.S. Price. Additionally, there is one scrapbook which contains printed materials regarding Valentine Gallery exhibitions from 1925-1936.
The artist's file for Eilshemius contains biographical information; correspondence between Valentine Dudensing and the artist, as well scattered letters from Carl Van Vecten, Alfred H. Barr, and museums and institutions; writings and notes; price lists and other financial and legal documents; printed material from Eilshemius's varied career and from his affiliation with the Valentine Gallery; photographs including portraits of the artist, and photos of installations and of works of art; and a scrapbook containing clippings and scattered other printed materials covering Eilshemius's shows at the Valentine Gallery.
Artists' files for John Kane, Henri Matisse, and C.S. Price contain scattered documentation. The file for John Kane includes correspondence between Valentine Dudensing and Kane's estate managers as well as museums and institutions, price lists, legal records, and printed materials. There are two letters from Henri Matisse to Valentine Dudensing regarding travel plans and a thank you message. The C.S. Price file consists of letters from Price regarding specific works of art, and scattered financial records.
A scrapbook dates from 1925-1936 and includes newspaper and magazine clippings about exhibitions and artists represented by the Valentine Gallery. Artists and exhibitions mentioned in the clippings include Alexander Brook, Giorgio de Chirico, Stuart Davis, Jean Lucrat, Carlos Merida, and Joseph Stella. Also, there is a poster created by Valentine Dudensing to fundraise for ambulances for France.
Brook, Alexander, 1898-1980; Davis, Stuart, 1892-1964; De Chirico, Giorgio, 1888-; Dudensing, F. Valentine, 1901-circa 1960; Eilshemius, Louis M. (Louis Michel), 1864-1941; F. Valentine Dudensing (Firm).; Kane, John, 1860-1934; Matisse, Henri, 1869-1954; Mérida, Carlos, 1891-; Price, C. S., (Clayton S.), 1874-1950; Stella, Joseph, 1877-1946; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Art galleries, Commercial -- New York (State)-- New York; Painting, Modern -- 20th century; Photographs; Scrapbooks
- Artists Files, circa 1890-1960; Series 1; 1.3 Linear feet Box 1, 3
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 4 subseries.
  1.1. Louis Eilshemius, circa 1890-1960
  1.2. John Kane, 1930-1942
  1.3. Henri Matisse, 1927-1930
  1.4. C.S. Price, 1940-1948
  Scope and Contents note
  Found are scattered biographical materials, correspondence, printed materials, financial records, and photographs for artists Louis Eilshemius, John Kane, Henri Matisse, and C.S. Price.
  - Louis Eilshemius, circa 1890-1960; Subseries 1
    This subseries consists of materials relating to Louis Eilshemius's career, his relationship with Valentine Dudensing, and his affiliation with the Valentine Gallery. Found are biographical sketches, correspondence, writings, contracts, price lists and lists of works of art, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, music written by Eilshemius, published works by Eilshemius, photographs of the artist, installations, and works of art, and a scrapbook. Some of the Eilshemius letters are illustrated. A scrabook contains clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs.
    - Biographical Sketches and Essays, 1917-circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Ode to Valentine Dudensing," by Louis Eilshemius, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Poetry, by Louis Eilshemius, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Essay on Eilshemius by Charles Norman, 1937-1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes correspondence regarding the article
    - Notecards of Exhibitions, circa 1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Critical Reviews, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Contracts, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Price Lists, 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - List of Paintings at Valentine Gallery, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - List of Paintings Stolen, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - List of Books by Eilshemius, circa 1932 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Loan Receipt, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Clippings, 1934-1946 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
      Oversized material housed in Box 3
    - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1930-circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, 1897-1942 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - Exhibition Notecards, 1932-1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Advertisements for Framing Services, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Eilshemius promotional material
    - Self-Promotion Pamphlets, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Entitled "Some Discoveries in Science and Art," by Dr. Louis Eilshemius, M.A., Etc.
    - Music, To My Mother--Six Musical Moods, composition by Louis Eilshemius, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Music, Zapparella, by Louis Eilshemius, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Music, Oenone--And Eight Other Tone-Pictures, by Louis Eilshemius, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Mystery and Truth: A Sonnet Sequence, by Louis Eilshemius, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Companionship, by Louis Eilshemius, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Song of Spring and Blossoms of Unrequited Love, with art by Louis Eilshemius, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Photographs (Box 1)
      - Portraits of Louis Eilshemius by Carl Van Vecten, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Portraits of Louis Eilshemius, circa 1890-circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Installations, circa 1932 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Works of Art, Landscapes and Marine Scenes, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 39-41)
      - Works of Art, Nudes, Nymphs, and Samoa, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
      - Works of Art, Africa, Italy, Spain, New York City, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - Works of Art, Figures, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Works of Art, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
    - Scrapbook, 1925-1940 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Oversized Clippings, circa 1930 (Box 3)
      Material from Box 1, F22
    - Oversized Music by Louis Eilshemius, 1900 (Box 3)
      Material from Box 1, F31
    - Oversized Scrapbook, 1925-1936 (Box 3)
      Material from Box 1, F48
  - John Kane, 1930-1942; Subseries 2
    This subseries consists of materials relating to John Kane and his affiliation with the Valentine Gallery. Materials include correspondence, pricelists and lists of works of art, loan records, and an exhibition catalog. Letters are from Kane's business manager, the executor of his estate, and from individuals and institutions that owned works of art by Kane.
    - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Lists of Works of Art, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Addresses and Lists of Contacts, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Price Lists, 1934-1942 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Loan Records, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Exhibition Catalog, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 65)
      Annotated with prices
  - Henri Matisse, Subseries 3
    There are two letters from Henri Matisse to Valentine Dudensing written in French from Nice, France. In the first letter, Matisse thanks Dudensing for the presentation of the exhibition, and expresses his gratitude to Mrs. Dudensing. In the second, he announces his return from a long trip to Tahiti, Panama, Martinique, Guadaloupe and the U.S.. He discusses plans to return to Paris at the end of the month and hopes he has a chance to meet up with Dudensing.
    - Correspondence, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - C.S. Price, 1940-1948; Subseries 4
    This subseries consists of materials relating to C.S. Price's affiliation with the Valentine Gallery. Found is correspondence, price lists, and scattered financial notes. The bulk of the correspondence is from C.S. Price to Valentine Dudensing, but there are some letters between Dudensing and musuems regarding works by Price.
    - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Correspondence, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Price Lists, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Financial Notes, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 77)
- Scrapbook, 1925-1936; Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet Box 2, 4
  Found is a scrapbook containing newspaper clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and scattered photographs of works of art relating to exhibitions held at the Valentine Gallery. Clippings include artists: Peter Amo, Alexander Brook, Giorgio de Chirico, Glenn Colleman, Miguel Covarrubias, Stuard Davis, Andre Derain, Robert Laurent, Jean Lucrat, Henri Matisse, Carlos Mérida, Emile Payot, Andre Dunoyer de Segonzac, and Joseph Stella.
  - Scrapbook, 1925-1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4
  - Loose Clippings, 1925-1936 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Loose Photos of Works of Art, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Scrapbook, 1925-1936 (Box 4)
    Material from Box 2, F1-2